Guide to the John Nolen Papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
Nolen, John papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
- Series IV. Professional Career
  - Landscape Architect and City Planner
    - Routine Office Material
      - Postcards
        - Postcards from New Hampshire (Box 50, Folder 29)
          63 cards.
        - Postcards from Concord, NH (Box 50, Folder 30)
          1 card depicting the State Capitol
        - Postcards from Peterborough, NH (Box 50, Folder 31)
        - Postcards from Portsmouth, NH (Box 50, Folder 32)
        - Postcards from New Jersey (Box 50, Folder 33)
        - Postcards from Atlantic City (Box 50, Folder 34)
        - Postcards from Montclair (Box 50, Folder 35)
        - Postcards from Newark, NJ (Box 50, Folder 36)
        - Postcards from Orange, NJ (Box 50, Folder 37)
        - Postcards from Princeton, NJ (Box 50, Folder 38)
          2 cards,
        - Postcards from Radburn (Box 50, Folder 39)
          40 cards
        - Postcards from Trenton, NJ (Box 50, Folder 40)
        - Postcards from New Mexico (Box 50, Folder 41)
        - Postcards from Albuquerque, NM (Box 50, Folder 42)
        - Postcards from Santa Fe, NM (Box 50, Folder 43)
          2 cards and 1 booklet of cards.
        - Postcards from New York (Box 50, Folder 44)
          72 cards and 1 booklet of cards from Tuxedo Park, NY
        - Postcards from Albany, NY (Box 50, Folder 45)
        - Postcards from Buffalo, NY (Box 50, Folder 46)
        - Postcards from Geneva, NY (Box 50, Folder 47)
          18 cards and 1 Souvenir Book of Geneva, NY
        - Postcards from Syracuse, NY (Box 50, Folder 48)
        - Postcards from Troy, NY (Box 50, Folder 49)
        - Postcards from Asheville, NC (Box 50, Folder 50)
        - Postcards from Charlotte, NC (Box 50, Folder 51)
          46 cards and 1 Folding View Book of Charlotte, NC
        - Postcards from Durham (Box 50, Folder 52)
        - Postcards from Greensboro (Box 50, Folder 53)
          3 cards and 1 Souvenir Book
        - Postcards from Raleigh (Box 50, Folder 54)
        - Postcards from Wilmington (Box 50, Folder 55)
        - Postcards from Ohio (Box 50, Folder 56)
        - Postcards from Akron (Box 50, Folder 57)
        - Postcards from Cincinnati (Box 50, Folder 58)
        - Postcards from Cleveland (Box 50, Folder 59)
        - Postcards from Columbus, Ohio (Box 50, Folder 60)
        - Postcards from Dayton (Box 50, Folder 61)
          2 cards
        - Postcards from Oregon (Box 50, Folder 62)
        - Postcards from Pennsylvania (Box 50, Folder 63)
        - Postcards from Erie, PA (Box 50, Folder 64)
        - Postcards from Harrisburg (Box 50, Folder 65)
        - Postcards from Johnstown (Box 50, Folder 66)
        - Postcards from Lancaster (Box 50, Folder 67)
        - Postcards from Lock Haven (Box 50, Folder 68)
        - Postcards from Milton (Box 50, Folder 69)
        - Postcards from Pittsburgh (Box 50, Folder 70)
        - Postcards from Reading, PA (Box 50, Folder 71)
          28 cards.
        - Postcards from Scranton, PA (Box 50, Folder 72)
        - Postcards from Sharon, PA (Box 50, Folder 73)
        - Postcards from Warren, PA (Box 50, Folder 74)
        - Postcards from Rhode Island (Box 50, Folder 75)
        - Postcards from Newport, RI (Box 50, Folder 76)
        - Postcards from Providence, RI (Box 50, Folder 77)
        - Postcards from Charleston, SC (Box 50, Folder 78)
        - Postcards from Columbia, SC (Box 50, Folder 79)
        - Postcards from Spartanburg, SC (Box 50, Folder 80)
        - Postcards from South Dakota (Box 50, Folder 81)
          1 depicting the state capitol at Pierre, SD
        - Postcards from Tennessee (Box 50, Folder 82)
        - Postcards from Chattanooga, Tenn. (Box 50, Folder 83)
        - Postcards from Nashville, TN (Box 50, Folder 84)
        - Postcards from Kingsport, TN (Box 50, Folder 85)
          32 cards.
        - Postcards from Texas (Box 50, Folder 86)
        - Postcards from Dallas, TX (Box 50, Folder 87)
        - Postcards from El Paso, TX (Box 50, Folder 88)
        - Postcards from Utah (Box 50, Folder 89)
        - Postcards from Ogden, UT (Box 50, Folder 90)
        - Postcards from Salt Lake City, UT (Box 50, Folder 91)
        - Postcards from Vermont (Box 50, Folder 92)
        - Postcards from Burlington, VT (Box 50, Folder 93)
        - Postcards from Woodstock, VT (Box 50, Folder 94)
        - Postcards from Virginia (Box 50, Folder 95)
        - Postcards from Hollins, VA (Box 50, Folder 96)
        - Postcards from Lynchburg, VA (Box 50, Folder 97)
        - Postcards from Richmond, VA (Box 50, Folder 98)
        - Postcards from Roanoke, VA (Box 50, Folder 99)
        - Postcards from Washington (Box 50, Folder 100)
          20 cards.
        - Postcards from Seattle, WA (Box 50, Folder 101)
        - Postcards from West Virginia (Box 50, Folder 102)
          1 card from the State Capitol
        - Postcards from Wisconsin (Box 50, Folder 103)
          121 cards.
        - Postcards from Greenbay, WI (Box 50, Folder 104)
        - Postcards from Janesville, WI (Box 50, Folder 105)
        - Postcards from Kenosha, WI (Box 50, Folder 106)
        - Postcards from Madison, WI (Box 50, Folder 107)
        - Postcards from Milwaukee, WI (Box 50, Folder 108)
        - Postcards from Portage, WI (Box 50, Folder 109)
        - Postcards from Wyoming (Box 50, Folder 110)
    - Project Material
      - Correspondence
        - Correspondence regarding book research, 1918 - 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
          For his book "Housing for War Needs"
        - Harvard research for city planning, 1931 - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 26)
          Correspondence
        - 'New Town for Old' submission for reviews correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 32)
          (should go with other "New Town" folders)
        - Article and magazine subscription correspondence, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Article and magazine subscription correspondence, 1928 - 1929 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence with Yenching University in China, 1933 - 1937 (Box 7, Folder 7)
          Academic
        - Reconstruction Finance Corporation correspondences, 1932 - 1933 (Box 7, Folder 8)
          New York Times clipping, program brochure and correspondence
        - Correspondence with Rotch Traveling Scholarship recepients, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 11)
        - Article contribution to City and Regional Planning magazine, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 12)
          article and correspondence
        - Pocono Study Tours correspondence, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 13)
          international tours of educational facilities
        - Meeting in London correspondence, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 14)
        - International Intercollegiate Tours, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 23)
        - Aberdeen, Marchioness of, 1915 - 16 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Aberdeen, Marchioness of, September 1922 - 1924 (Box 8, Folder 2)
          Personal correspondence, letter with pressed heather branches
        - Aberdeen, Marchioness of, January 1924 - April 1933 (Box 8, Folder 3)
          Personal correspondence + correspondence about planning issues
        - Adams, Thomas, 1911 - 12 (Box 8, Folder 4)
          correspondence regarding planning. Adams: Town Planning Adviser, Commission of Conservation, Ottawa, Canada
        - Alexander, Capt. S.B. - Property, April 1924 - October 1927 (Box 8, Folder 5)
          correspondence with Julia Alexander, Attorney at Law, Charlotte NC. Regarding S.B. Alexander property
        - American Brass Company, 1916 - 1922 (Box 8, Folder 6)
          correspondence regarding residential development of American Brass Company land in Waterbury, CT.
        - Barnes, Prof. Earl & Family, September 1923 - July 1924 (Box 8, Folder 7)
          correspondence (photocopies) regarding book recommendations for Barnes in his design of Bennett Farm.
        - Bassett, E.M., 1924 - 1925 (Box 8, Folder 8)
          correspondence regarding zoning (referencing contemporary zoning plans in other US cities)
        - Black, Russell V., June 10, 1927 - December 14, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 9)
          correspondence with Black, involved with regional planning, based out of Philadelphia.
        - Borsodi, Ralph, July 27, 1934 - May 6, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 10)
          correspondence and bulletins from Borsodi's "School of Living" (Suffern, NY)
        - Bradley, Prof. Phillips, 1928 - 1929 (Box 8, Folder 11)
          correspondence with Professor Bradley (Amherst College) - opinions on city/regional planning
        - Brentano's, 1925 - 1926 (Box 8, Folder 12)
          Book requests from Nolen to Brentano's, bookstore in NYC
        - Cauchon, Noulan, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 13)
          correspondence with Cauchon (Ottawa), criticism of Nolen's Vienna letter
        - Cary, Hunsdon, 1923 - 1924 (Box 8, Folder 14)
          correspondence regarding development possibilities for a tract of land near Richmond, VA.
        - Cheney, C.H., 1928 - 1932 (Box 8, Folder 15)
          correspondence regarding AIA Comm. on City&Regional Planning. Mentioning Palos Verdes and Mariemont
        - Commonwealth Construction Company, 1924 - 1932 (Box 8, Folder 16)
          correspondence regarding stock prices/possible sale for Nolen's shares of Commonwealth Hotel Construction Company
        - Contreras, Carlos, October 22, 1929 - March 3, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 17)
          correspondence with Mexican planner Contreras, particularly regarding planning of Veracruz + photo postcards
        - Coyle, David Cushman, November 30, 1932 - Jan 15, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 18)
          correspondence; Coyle dealt with economics and public affairs.
        - Douglass, William H., December 10, 1935 - January 3, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 19)
          Endorsement letter for Douglass, regarding his position at US Dot. of the Interior - Nat'l Park Service
        - Ford, James, January 11, 1928 - Oct 24, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 20)
          correspondence with Ford - Director of "Better Homes in America" organization
        - Filene, Edward.A., January 3, 1924 - September 11, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 21)
          Correspondence on planning, econ. recovery + brochures on France, England peace contests.
        - Ford, James -- Book Review Correspondence, April 22, 1935 - July 9, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 22)
          correspondence regarding Ford's book, "The Slum in Perspective"
        - Foreign Correspondence, 1931 - 1937 (Box 8, Folder 23)
          Address records and misc. correspondence with contacts in England, Germany, Czech, Sweden, Belgium, Netherlands, photos from Batas
        - Gallup, George B., July 14, 1930 - Sep 12, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 24)
          correspondence with Gallup about planning/housing in Florida
        - Herrick, Dr. Cheesman A., February 7 - December 10, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 25)
          correspondence with Herrick, President of Girard College, regarding address Nolen gave there in 1936.
        - Huebsch, B.W., 1917 - 1921 (Box 8, Folder 26)
          Records, receipts, correspondence with B.W. Huebsch, Inc, Nolen's publisher for "Replanning Small Cities"
        - La Fleur, Dr. Albert, February 22, 1935 - December 30, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 27)
        - Modley, Rudolph - Pictoral Statistics Inc., April 1, 1934 - November 17, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 28)
          correspondence and work examples from Pictoral Statistics, Inc., specializing in graphic illustration (charts, maps, graphs, etc.)
        - Newton, Kenneth H.N., June 26, 1935 - January 18, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 29)
          correspondence Incl. Nolen's recommendation for Newton in new position as landscape architect for Dept. of the Interior
        - Pickett, Clarence E., July 12, 1934 - Feb. 29, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 30)
          correspondence and writings by Pickett about Subsistence Homesteading & Pickett's reflections on state of European countries upon return from a 1934 trip.
        - Powell, Rev. Lyman H., January 5, 1922 - July 12, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 31)
          correspondence with Powell, Executive Director of Century Company.
        - Ihlder, John, February 21, 1916 - February 23, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 32)
          correspondence regarding housing and city planning in Philadelphia; also general correspondence with Ihlder as Civic Development Manager at US Chamber of Commerce
        - Reed, Fred E., June 8 - July 12, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 33)
          correspondence regarding regional planning, real estate & airport development. Fred Reed Co, Realtors
        - Romeike, Albert & Co., 1921 - 1931 (Box 8, Folder 34)
          correspondence and receipts from Albert Romeike & Co Press Clipping Bureau
        - Root, Irving C., 1924 - 1926 (Box 8, Folder 35)
          correspondence with Root, landscape architect, some regarding city planning in Flint, Michigan
        - Stein, Clarence S., December 12, 1931 - July 11, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 36)
          correspondence with Stein, architect, relating to housing/planning
        - Unwin, Raymond, 1920 - 1922 (Box 8, Folder 37)
          correspondence about many subjects. Good friend of Nolen's judging from letters.
        - Unwin, Raymond, 1922 - 1937 (Box 8, Folder 38)
          correspondence - many subjects. Up to Nolen's last days in Feb.1937.
        - Walker, Hale J., July 22, 1927 - February 4, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 39)
          correspondence with Walker and also assorted misc. correspondence relating to ??. Incl. plan for Carthage College & project correspondence
        - White, Aubrey L., July 10-21, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 40)
          correspondence - planning in Spokane, WA
        - Williams, F.B., 1924 - 1926 (Box 8, Folder 41)
          correspondence
        - Wilson, Dr. M.L., July 14 - Nov 26, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 42)
          Correspondence Wilson -- Asst. Secretary, Dept. of Agriculture. Regarding Subsistence Homesteads.
        - Zug, Prof. George B., April 12, 1921 - October 25, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 43)
          correspondence between Zug (Prof. in Dept. of Modern Art, Dartmouth) regarding materials, images, info for planning a course in City Planning and Civic Art.
        - Akron, OH (Box 21, Folder 1)
          Project materials: background materials -- maps, newspaper articles, city and chamber of commerce publications, climatological data, civic survey, etc.
        - Akron, OH, June 1916 - January 1917 (Box 21, Folder 2)
          Project materials: prelim. reports, surveys, correspondence with Akron Chamber of Commerce and other entities, regarding plans for Akron projects incl. Civic Center and Union Depot.
        - Akron, OH, January 1917 - December 1917 (Box 21, Folder 3)
          correspondence, materials relating to Akron projects. Incl. lists of items to be prepared for city plan, notes on Union Station/streetcar issues.
        - Akron. OH, January 1918 - May 1919 (Box 21, Folder 4)
          Correspondence relating to visit to Akron in Jan.1919; draft of plan, other correspondence related to continued Akron planning involvement.
        - Akron, OH., February 1919 - April 1922 (Box 21, Folder 5)
          Mostly correspondence and some materials related to continued Akron planning involvement
        - Akron, OH. Report Comments. (Box 21, Folder 6)
          Correspondence -- mostly positive letters/comments in reaction to Nolen's report on Akron.
        - Allwood, NJ, January 1919 (Box 21, Folder 7)
          correspondence between Nolen and Alfred Ernst, Chief Engineer for Brighton Mills (Cotton manufacturer) regarding plans for housing
        - Allwood, NJ (Box 21, Folder 8)
          Red folder. background materials -- maps, "Warp and Weft" publications. Blueprints for house designs, envelope of copies of general plan for Allwood.
        - Alturas, FL, November 1925 (Box 21, Folder 9)
          Correspondence relating to Alturas housing, envelope of photos of the area (mostly orchards)
        - Appleton, WI, July 1920 (Box 21, Folder 10)
          correspondence with Chamber of Commerce regarding planning visits to Appleton.
        - Ardmore, PA: Lower Merion and Region, 1930 - 1932 (Box 21, Folder 11)
          correspondence regarding town planning for Lower Merion; some publications from Armore containing material on planning issues.
        - Ardmore, PA: Lower Merion and Region, 1932 - 1934 (Box 21, Folder 12)
          correspondence regarding town planning for Lower Merion
        - Arlington, MA, September 1922 (Box 21, Folder 13)
          Newspaper clippings, correspondence, notes from Arlington Board of Trade, town map, lyrics to "patriotic" Arlington-specific songs
        - Asheville, NC, February 1921 - March 1922 (Box 21, Folder 14)
          correspondence and materials relating to preparing to work on Asheville project -- newspaper clippings, requests for materials, arrangements for trip south.
        - Asheville, NC, 1922 (Box 21, Folder 15)
          correspondence and materials relating to Asheville project. Many newspaper clippings regarding Asheville and town planning matters from local Asheville newspapers. Also includes Field Survey book from 1922 (unbound)
        - Asheville, NC, October 1922 - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 16)
          correspondence and materials relating to Asheville project. References to city plan report being completed.
        - Asheville, NC, January 1924 - October 1926 (Box 21, Folder 17)
          correspondence in relation to Nolen's continued services in Asheville city planning.
        - Asheville, NC, 1926 - 1938 (Box 21, Folder 18)
          Correspondence materials (newspaper clippings) in relation to Nolen's continued services in Asheville city planning. Includes correspondence between Nolen's children and Asheville City Council following death of Nolen.
        - Asheville, NC -- Report (Box 21, Folder 19)
          correspondence regarding report distribution, comments from those who received it.
        - Asheville, NC -- Clippings from Asheville Citizen, December 1921 - August 1922 (Box 21, Folder 20)
          Newspaper clippings about misc. planning in Asheville, some involving Nolen. Pasted into scrapbook chronologically.
        - Asheville, NC (Box 21, Folder 21)
          Large red folder, many background materials on Asheville: Newspaper articles, city publications, maps, tourism brochures, etc. Also includes a copy of Nolen's Field Survey book from 1922.
        - Babson Park, MA, May 1922 - June 1923 (Box 21, Folder 22)
          correspondence and materials related to work on new tract of land to be developed for Babson Institute, Wellesley Hills, MA. Copies of layout plan, preliminary plan write-up.
        - Babson Park, MA, 1923 - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 23)
          correspondence related to Babson Institute project.
        - Babson Park, MA (Box 21, Folder 24)
          Examples of Babson Statistical Reports.
        - Babson Park, MA (Box 21, Folder 25)
          Large red folder. Mostly blueprints and reproductions of the Tentative Plan for Development at the Babson Institute. Some miscellaneous publications (Babson Annual Report) as well.
        - Bar Harbor, ME (Box 21, Folder 26)
          Large red folder. Background information, maps and publications on Bar Harbor/Mount Desert Island, Sieur de Monts publications.
        - Madison Park, Charlottesville, VA, 1910 (Box 21, Folder 27)
          Bylaws, deed, plant list for tracts in Madison Park, Charlottesville, VA
        - Beaver Lake, NC, 1922 (Box 22, Folder 1)
          correspondence regarding development of Beaver Lake Property
        - Belleair, FL, 1924 - 1926 (Box 22, Folder 2)
          correspondence and materials regarding Belleair development in FL. Contract for Deed, General Layout Plan, street names, record of setbacks on lots, valuation on lots, etc.
        - Belleair, FL, 1924 (Box 22, Folder 3)
          Contract for services to be rendered, contract for deed, some correspondence.
        - Belleair, FL, 1925 - 1928 (Box 22, Folder 4)
          Additional correspondence, drawings, relating to revisions and specifics of Belleair plan. Quotations for image reproduction
        - Belmont, FL, 1925 - 1928 (Box 22, Folder 5)
          Correspondence & materials related to planning work for Belmont-on-the-Gulf community. Quotes for image reproduction, general plan layout drawing.
        - Berkeley-Oakland, CA, 1927 (Box 22, Folder 6)
          Correspondence regarding potential planning duties for Berkeley
        - Berkeley, CA, 1928 - 1931 (Box 22, Folder 7)
          Correspondence and materials regarding Berkeley work relating to University campus expansion. Incl. first draft of report concerning street/traffic conditions & other traffic-related considerations.
        - Berkeley, CA, 1928 - 1929 (Box 22, Folder 8)
          Correspondence and materials regarding Berkeley work related to University expansion. City map; official agreement between Nolen and City
        - Berkeley, CA, 1923 - 1926 (Box 22, Folder 9)
          Correspondence and materials regarding general Berkeley city planning
        - Berkshire Greene, PA, 1923 - 1924 (Box 22, Folder 10)
          Correspondence regarding Berkshire Heights subdivision, Reading, PA.
        - Birmingham, Ala., 1915 - 1918 (Box 22, Folder 11)
          Correspondence and materials regarding subdivision work in Birmingham done for American Cast Iron Pipe Co. (ACIPCO). Site photographs, notes, "Preliminary Report of an Industrial Village"
        - Boston, MA, 1933 - 1935 (Box 22, Folder 12)
          Materials mostly relating to the study "A Report on the Income and Cost of Six Districts in the City of Boston"
        - Boston, MA. (Advisory Committee on Housing), 1933 - 1935 (Box 22, Folder 13)
          Correspondence and materials regarding slum clearance and other housing issues in Boston.
        - Boston, MA (Metropolitan Planning Commission), 1930 - 1932 (Box 22, Folder 14)
          Materials related to the proposal for an extended Boston Metropolitan District
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1913 - 1914 (Box 22, Folder 15)
          Correspondence materials related to the beginning of Nolen's involvement with Bridgeport planning. Program of work to be done, lecture given at Bridgeport in 1913, other initial steps.
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1914 (Box 22, Folder 16)
          Correspondence materials related to Bridgeport work (Fairfield Avenue Bridge) Preliminary report & related material.
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1916 (Box 22, Folder 17)
          Correspondence materials related to Bridgeport work, mainly regarding potential additional housing -- Bridgeport Housing Company
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1916 - 1918 (Box 22, Folder 18)
          Correspondence mostly thank-you letters to Nolen for sending his book "Better City Planning for Bridgeport" and other follow-up correspondence
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1916 (Box 22, Folder 19)
          Correspondence materials related to Bridgeport Housing Company
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1914 - 1920 (Box 22, Folder 20)
          Reports of various lengths submitted to Bridgeport City Plan Commission
        - Bridgeport, CT -- Chamber of Commerce, 1916 - 1920 (Box 22, Folder 21)
          Correspondence materials related to Bridgeport Chamber of Commerce Committee on Housing, report "More Houses for Bridgeport"
        - Bridgeport, CT -- Chamber of Commerce, 1916 - 1920 (Box 22, Folder 22)
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1915 - 1920 (Box 22, Folder 23)
          "Plan for Workingmen's Homes"; article: War-Boom Towns: Bridgeport"; newspaper clippings about housing
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1911 - 15 (Box 22, Folder 24)
          Materials related to establishment of Bridgeport House Building Company, surveys entitled "Housing Needs of Workingmen" (completed by factory owners)
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1914 - 1916 (Box 22, Folder 25)
          Misc. maps, blueprints of railroad structures, copies of map "General Plan for Redevelopment"
        - Bridgeport, CT, 1915 (Box 22, Folder 26)